<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian life manifested wherein is shewed who they are which follow the lamb in meekness and patience.</title>
            <author>Smith, William, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475204</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2256:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian life manifested wherein is shewed who they are which follow the lamb in meekness and patience.</title>
                  <author>Smith, William, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Quaker authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:151358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN LIFE MANIFESTED Wherein is ſhewed who they are which follows the Lamb in meekneſs and Patience.</head>
            <p>THe night of Apoſtacy having overſpread the earth, and the darkneſs of it having covered the people, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome below hath ſought out many Inventions, and the name of Chriſtians have been taken up from ſomething obſerved which the wiſdome below hath invented; and with this name people are ſatisfied, though from the life they be alienated, and ſuch are Gentiles who know not God, but are ſeperated from him, through the darkneſs that is in them; and whilſt they profeſs to know God, and to worſhip him, they are ignorant of him, and in works denies him &amp; though they have taken upon themſelves the name of Chriſtians, yet they are not changed from the Gentiles nature but abides in darkneſs and walkes in darkneſs, and knows not whither they go, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded their minds, and ſuch errs from the way of truth, notwithſtanding they profeſs a Chriſtian ſtate, and a Chriſtian worſhip, and the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt is hid from their eyes, and they do not know the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, but walks in their own way, and follows the devices of their own hearts, and worſhips the works of their own hands after the manner of the Gentiles, and though that which may be known of God be manifeſt in them, yet they like not to retain God in their knowledge, but likes to retain their own inventions better, and ſo they forſake the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living water, and hews to themſelves broken Ciſterns that can hold no water, and this brings a famine upon the land becauſe people feels not the Lord, nor the ſprings of his refreſhings, and though they may aſſemble together and ſit before him as his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet their hearts are not towards him, and therefore in vain they worſhip him: Now foraſmuch as that which may be known of God is manifeſt in people, and that both Jew and Gentile are
<pb facs="tcp:151358:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:151358:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151358:3"/>enlightened with the light of Chriſt, and that there is no reſpect of perſons with God, then that which is manifeſt from God within people is to be chiefly minded in its manifeſtation, for ſeeing that none can know God but by the Revellation of Jeſus Chriſt, and that none can witneſs ſalvation but by the power of Chriſt, then is every one to mind that light with which Chriſt enlightens them, that by the manifeſtation of it they may know God, and worſhip him as he is God, for as the light comes from God, ſo doth it give the knowledge of God in the hearts of all that beleive in it, and there is not any that are true. Chriſtians until they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive in the light which is manifeſt from God within them, for as the Apoſtaſie is entred, and the darkneſs overſpread, ſo with the light that ſhines in the heart is darkneſs expelled, and then the light doth give the knowledge of the Glory of God in the face of Chriſt Jeſus, and in the light thus ſhining the Lord is known and truely worſhiped, for as blindneſs hath hapned in part unto the Jews, until the fulneſs of the Gentiles be brought in, the Lord willing to make known his loveing kindneſs unto a people that ſought him not, and that they might be his people which were not his people, and that both Jews and Gentiles in fulneſs of time might be gathered together in one, even in Chriſt, ſo doth his power work both in Jews and Gentiles who in his light beleive; by which power they come to be changed from all things which they have outwardly obſerved, and comes to be renewed in the ſpirits of their minds, and to feel the inward man reſtored into Chriſt, who of twain maketh one new man in himſelf and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth peace, for he is not a Jew which is one outward, neither is circumciſion that of the fleſh, but he is a Jew which is one inward, and circumciſion is that of the heart, which is wrought by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Gods ſpirit within man, and there is the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> known both in Jew and Gentile, for the love of God doth uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally ſpread abroad unto all Nations, Kindreds and People, and in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh Righteouſneſs is accepted of him, and Chriſtianity doth not lye in any outward obſervation, nor in any particular form which in any Nation, or amongſt any people is ſet up, but it is in Chriſt the ſeed, and if any man be in Chriſt he is a new creature, and a a new creature is a Chriſtian, for Chriſt is his life, and this is that which hath been witneſſed by all the holy men of God in ages paſt, who were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151358:3"/>of the Divine nature, and had all things therein given them that pertained to life and godlineſs, and there is none can come to a chriſtian ſtate, but who comes to the light which from the life is made manifeſt, for the light is given of God to ſearch out all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented wayes and formed works, and with the light they are all reproved, and that which makes them manifeſt and reproves them, that is the way which leads out of them, and as the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it is received, ſo all invented waies and formed works comes to be denied, and the mind comes actually to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the leadings of the light in its own way, and then the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment riſes in the power, which caſts out the Idol, and deſtroyes the inventor, and they both fall together by the work of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and then the nature of the Heathen dies, and Chriſt appears in the glory of his own life, and tranſlates the beleiver into the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his own likeneſs, and that is a chriſtian ſtate in which man comes into union with Chriſt, and lives the life of Chriſt, and there the Jew and the Gentile is made one, and comes into the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and Chriſt is then felt who is a chriſtians nature, and from the nature there is fruit produced in love, and peace, and meekneſs, and gentleneſs, and that which doth not bear this fruit it is none of Chriſts, for all ſtrife, and envy, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice is from the darkneſs, and they that live in ſuch things are not Chriſtians, though they may take the name upon them, but they are in the Heathens nature, where God they know not, and ſuch deſtroyes one another, who are not in the love, and peace and unity of the ſpirit for where the ſpirit is not received the fruit of it cannot be maniſeſted, and therefore every mans way, ſeeming right in his own eyes, he would have all to walk with him in his path, and there riſes all contention from mens own opinions, for which they perſecute and deſtroies one another about their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the life of a chriſtian is not ſo, for the birth born of God is love, and love thinketh no ill, but is kind and courteous, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle towards all men, and they that are born of this life they are true chriſtians, and their life doth manifeſt their nature, and though they be hated and wronged they do not ſeek revenge, and though they be reviled they do not revile again, but endures patiently, and waits to ſee the converſion of their enemies, for chriſtians ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſecuted any but hath alwayes been perſecuted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, who have cloathed themſelves with the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151358:4"/>and it hath ever been a mark of a true Diſciple of Chriſt to be hated and perſecuted for his names ſake, and whoſoever will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer perſecution, but whoſoever doth live godly in Chriſt Jeſus doth not perſecute any, for it is contrary to their life, for they that are born of God, they have the mind of Chriſt, and in his life they hold forth their teſtimony in all long-ſuffering, meekneſs and patience, not ſtriving nor reſiſting nor revenging, but loving, and praying, and bleſſing, and in this a chriſtian life is manifeſted, and the heathens life is judged and condemned, for who are guided by the ſpirit of God they do not perſecute any, though they be contrary minded, but in all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and gentleneſs they labour in love, and ſeeks to win them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth which they are partakers of, and by ſoundneſs of doctrine and holineſs of life, they hold forth their teſtimony, and this manifeſts a chriſtian life, where love and good will is held forth unto all people, and this life is far from perſecuting any, for it can love an enemy, and as there can be no perfect unity nor fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip but in the ſpirit of God, ſo they that are guided by the ſpirit and lives in it, they labour in love to gather others into fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them, for what can perſecution do to the changing and renewing the mind of a man, it can never work reformation in the heart, though it may force the outward man to conform in practiſe, for it is only the love which overcometh and perſwadeth the mind into the way of truth, and though perſecution may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over ſome as to make them conform in practiſe, yet it doth not make them Chriſtians, neither doth it caſt out hereſie, where any is found in ſuch a ſtate; and what advantage hath the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors by forcing contrary minds into their practiſe and worſhip, whileſt ſuch is not in their own hearts reformed thereunto, and to force a conformity when in heart people is nor reformed, it is but to make a hypocrite, for if a man be not perſwaded in his own heart that the practiſe which he obſerveth is according to truth, he can never joyn in unity with ſuch as are ſo perſwaded, though he may conform his body to their obſervation: Then foraſmuch as perſecution cannot make a chriſtian, neither caſt out hereſie where it is, then it would be more commendable to let perſecution ceaſe, ſeeing that it doth not manifeſt a chriſtian life in practiſe, neither can make a chriſtian by ſuch a practiſe, therfore let every one waite to be gathered in the ſpirit of life and love in which there is no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151358:4"/>perſecution, but peace and unity, and proſperity every way, for it ever hath been and is the ruine of people and nations where any Religion hath been endeavoured to be promoted by perſecution, and ſuch as have endeavoured it have ever fallen in it, but could never eſtabliſh themſelves by it, and ſo the fall of one hath been the riſe of another, and theſe things brings deſolation and not peace.</p>
            <p>Objection. <hi>But if any ſhall ſay that people and nations ought to be kept in order, in matter of worſhip, according to the preſent conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the laws of that nation wherein they live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the ſpirit of God that ordereth all in the worſhip of God, and they that are not ordered by the ſpirit of God they are in diſorder, however they may conforme to that worſhip which by the laws of any nation is ſet up, and if the worſhip be not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the ſpirit of God, it is not the worſhip of God, neither is that order in the order of God, for God is worſhiped in the ſpirit only, and not by the conſtraint of the conſtitution of any nation law, and when people are guided by the ſpirit of God, then they are guided in good order, and edifies and comforts one another, and dwells together in the love, and peace, and unity of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo they are under the law of the ſpirit, which only hath power to order the conſcience, and not the law of any nation in things pertaining to the worſhip of God, ſo as the ſpirit comes to be received and the teſtimony of it obeyed, then by the ſpirit the mind of man is diſpoſed in love and peace, and meekneſs, and godlineſs, and that is good order, and againſt ſuch there is no law, for the birth born of God hath love to all people, and it is this day manifeſted amongſt a poor and an afflicted remnant whom the Lord hath raiſed in his power, and choſen to himſelf, who are by ſuch as are ſtrangers to their life reproachfully called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> though they have a name given them which no ſtranger can read, for the Lord hath raiſed them in his own name, and the name of Jeſus is their life, and it is a name which is above every name, and a name unto which every knee muſt bow, and they beare his name in all long ſuffering and patience, and follows his leadings in all gentleneſs, and meekneſs, and with his name they are cloathed as with a garment, for they are of him and they live unto him, and the fruit of his own life declares his prayſes, he hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151358:5"/>appeared for them in the day or their diſtreſs, and he hath helped them when there was none to pitty them, and by the arm of his power he hath raiſed them, and they are his people, and they dare not deny him, but are in love with him and keeps his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and he prepares their way for them, and leads them in it with joy of heart, and though tribulation do attend them, yet with his power he preſerves them, and they are not weary though there race be long; So doth the Lord our God give unto us his peace in all that he calls us to, and we deſire that all might be pertakers with us, which we know none can that ſet themſelves againſt us, and as the Lord hath wrought his own work in us, and hath changed us from that nature in which we ſometimes lived, ſo we are conſtrained to ſerve him and worſhip him in the ſpirit in which he hath gathered us, and as the cauſe is his own, ſo we commit it to him, who is able to defend it, and to preſerve us in it, and we muſt confeſs it before men, and we know that we ſhall never be aſhamed of our teſtimony, for that of God in every conſcience is our witneſs how unblamably we have behaved our ſelves, and how through all our ſufferings and hardſhips we have borne and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with patience, and have not at any time taken advantage againſt thoſe who without law have wronged us, but have in our innocency been willing to bear the reproach of thoſe that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached us, and to endure the hard afflictions of thoſe that have afflicted us, and it is well known that we have not at any time ſought an occaſion againſt thoſe that have dealt cruelly with us, but have ſought their eternal good; and it is alſo well known that we have not behaved our ſelves diſorderly or tumultuouſly among any people, but in all ſobriety, meekneſs and fear, we have held forth our teſtimony, and have laboured in the work of the Goſpel, that all might be gathered into the fellowſhip of it, and come to the enjoyment of the love and peace that is in it, and in theſe things we have manifeſted a chriſtian life, in its nature, which is a ſtate beyond the Jews and Gentiles, and Apoſtates, who are not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto the glotious Reſurrection of Chriſt, nor to the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and as we have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo do we walk in him, and are rooted and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his love, and by his power we are preſerved to abide faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and to perſevere in the work unto which he hath called us, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151358:5"/>by how much we are afflicted for his ſake, by ſo much the more doth he cauſe his joy to ſpring and abound in our hearts, ſo that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh we be afflicted, yet we are not caſt down, and though we be perſecuted yet we are not forſaken, for the Lord is with us in all our tryals, and in faithfulneſs he performs his promiſe, even as with his ſeed of old, ſo that when we paſs through the fire he is with us, and when we go through the water it doth not overflow us, for the Lord is our Rock and refuge, and by him alone we are ſaved as it is at this day; Therefore ye people behold a chriſtian life, which in this day is manifeſted as in times of old, for the Lord hath raiſed a people who are of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth his covenant with them for ever, and he hath ſaid in his counſel, ſurely in bleſſing I will bleſs them, and in multiplying I will multiply them, and their branches ſhall ſpread abroad, and they ſhall flouriſh as plants of my own hand, and I will pluck up the wild plants from amongſt them, and will lay waſt the bryars and thorns that troubles them, and they ſhall grow in my love and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in my life, for I am their God and they are my people, and all generations ſhall call them bleſſed: Now foraſmuch as theſe things are ſo, and that the Lord hath called us unto peace, and the fruit of his ſpirit doth ſo mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt it ſelf through us; then why is it that we bear the affliction of this preſent time? for as we follow peace with all men, and walks blameleſly towards all men, ſo ought we to receive encouragement in the ſame, and not to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed for our obedience unto God, for as the life that we live is the life of Chriſt, ſo it is not in our own power to make choice of any thing in our own wills, but as we have received Chriſt, and lives in his life, ſo by him alone we are diſpoſed, and it is his leadings that we follow, &amp; we know his way is peace, and his life eternal reſt: Therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e all people of all ſorts, waite in the light to know a chriſtian life, and content not your ſelves with a chriſtian name, for except you be regenerated and born again, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the kingdome of God, and howſoever you may be cloathed with the name of chriſtians, yet whileſt the Heathen nature lodgeth in you the uncleanneſs remains upon you, and your chriſtian name will leave you in the day of your calamity, and then you will ſee the want of a chriſtian na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo if whilſt you ſeem to be ſomething in a chriſtian name you be found nothing in a chriſtian nature, you do but deceive your ſelves in your imaginations; and now the day of the Lord ſhines forth, and the light of it ſpreads abroad, and he is gathering the ſcattered in the covenant of his life and with the light of his day he is viſiting the Nations, and he proclaims his ſalvation in the word of his power, and that is his living teſtimony in every
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151358:6"/>man, and the witneſs of it is true and faithful, and unto this muſt every man turn his mind, if ever he come to have life in Chriſt, or come to witneſs a chriſtian ſtate, and therefore every one is to bow unto that which reproves them, for anger, and envy and malice, and deceit, for that is Gods witneſs whoſe word is life, and let your ear be open to its counſel, and caſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you its holy teſtimony, but encline with dilligence, and obey it with carefulneſs, that by it you may be lead out of all your own wayes where you are ſcattered, &amp; may come into unity and fellowſhip with thoſe who are by it gathered, and ſo worſhip God in his living ſpirit in which there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and there you will know a chriſtian life by tranſlation, &amp; then you will ceaſe from perſecution, and live in love and peace and unity with thoſe that obey the goſpel, and where there is unity there is no perſecution: So all Rulers, Teachers and People, be ſober and moderate, and let not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent chriſtians be the obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of your ſeverity, but wait for the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which is come, and is yet coming, that you may all feel the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God to change your hears, who hath all hearts in his hand, and that the weight of Gods power may go over all that in you which at any time provokes you to anger and evil will, and draws you to exerciſe cruelty upon the meek of the earth, and that it may all be ſubdued and beaten down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the obedience of Chriſt, that the low meek humble ſpirit may ariſe in you, and by its own power diſpoſe you and order you, for this is the day of the Lords gathering, though it be a day of ſore affliction, and though many be yet a far off, yet is the Lord fetching them in, for the cords of his love is very ſtrong, and he is gathering together in one, even in Chriſt, in whoſe love and life many are ſet down in reſt, and inherits the riches of his grace in heavenly places, and many are drawing night to their habitation, who have been wandring as ſheep without a ſhepheard, but now are returning to the ſhepheard and Biſhop of their ſouls, whoſe paſtures are freſh and green, with which he doth ſatisfie every breathing ſoul that cannot live by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther food, So if you will hear and obey Gods ſpirit in your ſelves, then may you do well, and may come into unity and fellowſhip with us, who of the ſpirit are born, and loves the Lord Jeſus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt in ſincerity, but if you refuſe the heavenly call of Gods holy ſpirit in your conſcience, and will not come unto us who in the ſpirit of life and bond of peace are united, but yet ſay in your hearts that you will make us come unto you, then do you deceive your ſelves with an uncertain hope, for as we abide in the life in which we are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and in which we have fellowſhip with God and one another, it is moſt certain that if you will not come unto us we can never return unto you, and foraſmuch as God in his mercy hath manifeſted his life in us, ſo is our beleif in it, and our teſtimony is unto it, and the life that we now live is by the faith of the ſon of God, and the dearneſs of his love is more pretious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us then all periſhing things, and in his power we wait to be preſerved, in whoſe life we are united, and from whoſe nature a chriſtian life is maniſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and this is the Lamb whom we follow, who leads us in his hand, and comforts us with the riches of his goodneſs, and we live by him, and his own works prayſes him, who is over all bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for M. W.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
